Guide to the Harry R. Mattson Letters 1917-1919 MS 3235
New-York Historical Society
Harry R. Mattson letters
1917-1919
New-York Historical Society
Mattson, Harry Robert, Sr., 1894-1956
MS 3235
0.209 Linear feet in 1 half-document box (116 letters).
Letters written by United States Army soldier Harry R. Mattson (1894-1956) to his parents in Brooklyn, during World War I, when, as a member of the 106th Regiment, 27th Division, he served in Europe during the Ypres-Lys Offensive and the Somme Offensive.
Access Restrictions
This collection is stored offsite. To arrange to consult it, please go to www.nyhistory.org/library/visit.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Probably purchased from Beltrone & Company, dealers of military artifacts and documents, at an unrecorded date after 1998.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged chronologically.
Biographical note
Harry R. Mattson was born Henry Robert Reinke in Brooklyn on August 19, 1894. His parents were German immigrants Robert John Reinke and Louisa Hintze. Harry was later adopted by Louisa's third husband, Bernhard Mattson, and used his surname. Harry married in Queens, in 1924, Louise Künzert, and with her had one son, Harry R. Mattson Jr. The senior Harry worked as a bookkeeper and payroll auditor. He died in Brooklyn on December 12, 1956, and was buried in Woodlawn Cemetery in the Bronx.
Scope and Contents
This collection consists of 116 letters written between August 1917 and February 1919 by soldier Harry R. Mattson (1894–1956) to his parents at home in Brooklyn. Many letters were mailed from Camp Wadsworth, the United States Army training facility at Spartanburg, South Carolina, while the rest were sent from "somewhere in France" and "somewhere in Belgium." As a corporal in Company G, 106th Regiment, United States Army, 27th Division, Mattson served in Europe from May 10, 1918 to March 6, 1919, and would have participated in the Ypres-Lys Offensive and the Somme Offensive. He was honorably discharged on April 2, 1919, and received the Silver Star Medal for gallantry in action against an enemy of the United States.
Letters (correspondence); Lys, Battle of the, 1918.; Soldiers -- New York (State) -- Correspondence.; Somme, 2nd Battle of the, France, 1918.; World War, 1914-1918 -- Campaigns -- Belgium.; World War, 1914-1918 -- Campaigns -- France.; Camp Wadsworth (Spartanburg, S.C.); United States. Army. Infantry Regiment, 106th.
- Harry R. Mattson letters, 1917 August (Offsite-box 1, Folder 1)
  Scope and Contents
  One letter dated August 23, 1917, plus Mattson's calling card.
- Harry R. Mattson letters, 1917 October (Offsite-box 1, Folder 2)
  Thirteen letters dated 1917 October 2, 3, 8, 11, 12, 14 (2 letters), 19, 20, 22, 24, 28, and 30.
- Harry R. Mattson letters, 1917 November (Offsite-box 1, Folder 3)
  Twenty letters dated 1917 November 1, 4, 6, 11, 15, 17, 22 (2 letters), 27, and 29.
- Harry R. Mattson letters, 1917 December (Offsite-box 1, Folder 4)
  Nine letters dated 1917 December 6, 8, 10, 12, 16, 19, 22, 25, and 29.
- Harry R. Mattson letters, 1918 January (Offsite-box 1, Folder 5)
  Ten letters dated 1918 January 2, 6, 8, 10, 13, 16, 18, 23 (2 letters), and 27.
- Harry R. Mattson letters, 1918 February (Offsite-box 1, Folder 6)
  Four letters dated 1918 February 10, 21, 23, and 27.
- Harry R. Mattson letters, 1918 March (Offsite-box 1, Folder 7)
  Nine letters dated 1918 March 2, 8, 10, 13, 16, 18, 23, 27, and 31.
- Harry R. Mattson letters, 1918 April (Offsite-box 1, Folder 8)
  Fourteen letters dated 1918 April 1, 3 (2 letters), 7, 10, 14, 17, 18, 21, 24, 28 (3 letters), and 30.
- Harry R. Mattson letters, 1918 May (Offsite-box 1, Folder 9)
  Two letters dated 1918 May 8 and 26.
- Harry R. Mattson letters, 1918 June (Offsite-box 1, Folder 10)
  Two letters dated 1918 June 6 and 21.
- Harry R. Mattson letters, 1918 July (Offsite-box 1, Folder 11)
  Six letters dated 1918 July 6, 12, 14, 19, 24, and 29.
- Harry R. Mattson letters, 1918 August (Offsite-box 1, Folder 12)
  One letter dated August 20, 1918.
- Harry R. Mattson letters, 1918 September (Offsite-box 1, Folder 13)
  Five letters dated 1918 September 7, 11, 15, 19, and 21.
- Harry R. Mattson letters, 1918 October (Offsite-box 1, Folder 14)
  Five letters dated 1918 October 5, 7, 9, 15, and 24.
- Harry R. Mattson letters, 1918 November (Offsite-box 1, Folder 15)
  Six letters dated 1918 November 1, 7, 13, 16, 18, and 25.
- Harry R. Mattson letters, 1918 December (Offsite-box 1, Folder 16)
  Four letters dated 1918 December 1, 9, 15, and 25.
- Harry R. Mattson letters, 1919 January (Offsite-box 1, Folder 17)
  Three letters dated 1919 January 7, 15, and 23.
- Harry R. Mattson letters, 1919 February (Offsite-box 1, Folder 18)
  Two letters dated 1919 February 2 and 14.
- Box cover, etc. (Offsite-box 1, Folder 19)
  Cover of box that originally held the collection, inscribed "Pvt, Corporal, & Sgt Harry R. Mattson / Co. G, 106th US INF / AEF / Mr. & Mrs. B. Battson / 151 2nd Ave / Brooklyn, NY." Folder includes documentation from Beltrone & Company, sellers of the collection.